Guide to the John Lodge papers, 1935-2008 MS2271
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
John Lodge papers
1935-2008
1958-1970
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Lodge, John H., M.D.
MS2271
3 Linear Feet 7 document boxes
John H. Lodge (1925-2009) was an ophthalmologist and Clinical Instructor in Ophthalmology at the George Washington University Medical School from 1958 to 1970. He received a Bachelor of Arts from West Virginia University in 1947, and a Medical Degree from Johns Hopkins University in 1951. He completed post-graduate training at the Ohio State University Medical Center, the University of Wisconsin Medical School, and Harvard Medical School. He served 2 years as an ophthamologist in the United States Air Force in Misawa, Japan. Upon his return to the United States, Lodge taught Clinical Ophthalmology at the George Washington University School of Medicine. He also served as an Attending Ophthalmologist at the Washington Hospital Center for 25 years. Lodge's papers contain slides, photographs, programs, correspondence, booklets, tickets, brochures, souvenirs, maps, schedules, guides, course descriptions, rosters, flyers, reports, clippings, handbooks, notes and notebooks. They document his career and activities in Washington, D.C., as well as his travels and service in the United States Air Force.
Scope and Contents
The papers of John Lodge consist of materials that document Lodge's career in ophthamology in both the public and private sector. The collection dates from 1935 to 2008, with the bulk of the material dating between 1958 and 1970. It includes slides, photographs, programs, correspondence, booklets, tickets, brochures, souvenirs, maps, schedules, guides, course descriptions, rosters, flyers, reports, clippings, handbooks, notes and notebooks. Subjects include the George Washington University School of Medicine, the Washington Hospital Center, ophthamology, Washington, DC, Republican politics, Japan, India, and Thailand. Of particular note are the the correspondence, slides, and photographs pertaining to Lodge's service in the United States Air Force at the USAF Hospital in Misawa Japan from 1953 to 1955. Lodge was also an avid Washingtonian and Republican, and his correspondence and slides contain interesting observations and views of the city, its politics, and politians from the 1960s through the 1980s.
Arrangement
Collection: Organized into 6 series: Republican politics and cultural events in Washington, DC, Teaching, Travel, Medical Reference Files, Notebooks, and Personal.
Separated Materials
The following publications were sent to the Special Collections stacks:
Ophthalmologists of Maryland Washington and Virginia, n.d. Ophthalmolgists of Metropolitan Washington, 1975, 1978-79, 1992 The Physicians Directory, 1973 The Medical Directory of Washington, D.C. and Surrounding Counties, 1965, 1968, n.d. The Little Blue Book 1996 Washington D.C. Metropolitian Area Commission on Licensure Healing Arts Practice Act 1965
Biographical / Historical
John H. Lodge was an ophthalmologist and Clinical Instructor in Ophthalmology at the George Washington University Medical School from 1958 to 1970.
Lodge was born in Bridgeport, West Virginia on July 19, 1925. He graduated from West Virginia University in 1947, and went on to earn his medical degree at the Johns Hopkins University Medical School in 1951. His time at Johns Hopkins was followed by a year as an intern at the University Hospital at the Ohio State University. From there, Lodge went on to a residency in Ophthalmology at the University of Wisconsin Hospital.
Lodge's education was interrupted in 1953 when he was drafted into the United States Air Force as the primary ophthalmologist for northern Honshu and Hokkaido, Japan. He was based at the 6038th USAF Hospital, in Misawa Japan, and also served as a consulting ophthalmologist for the same area for the United States Army. Lodge served in Japan from 1953 to 1955. While on duty, he was also sent to the Philippines, Viet Nam, Thailand, India (where he was temporarily placed as a physician at the American Embassy), and Saudi Arabia.
Returning to the United States in 1955, he completed his residency at the University of Wisconsin and the Massachusetts Eye and Ear Hospital at Harvard University. In 1958 he began his practice in Bethesda, Maryland. From 1958 to 1970, Lodge taught Clinical Ophthalmology to third-year students at the George Washington University School of Medicine. He also served as an Attending Ophthalmologist and on several committees, including the Residents Selection Committee, at the Washington Hospital Center for 25 years. Lodge was a member of multiple professional organizations, including the American Academy of Ophthalmology, the American Medical Association, and the Maryland Academy of Ophthalmology.
John Lodge died in Washington, D.C. in 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers of John Lodge were donated to the University Archives by the George Washington University's Office of Facilities, 03/10/2009, (Accession Number 2009.035).
Inaugurations -- Washington (D.C.) -- 1960-1970.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ) -- 1960-1970.; Presidents Inauguration; Color slides; Medical ailments; Medical care; Medicine; United States -- District of Columbia -- Washington; Ophthalmology; India; Japan; Thailand; Kashmir; Washington Hospital Center; George Washington University. School of Medicine; District of Columbia Young Republicans; Young Republican Club of the District of Columbia; Episcopal Eye, Ear, and Throat Hospital (Washington, D.C.); United States. Air Force
- Republican politics and cultural events in Washington, D.C., 1949-1996; 1958-1966; Series 1; 1 Linear Feet 2 document boxes
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains flyers, slides, booklets, tickets, brochures, newsletters, and letters related to the subject of Washington D.C. history. The majority of the material relates to the District of Columbia Young Republicans, and other aspects of the Republican party such as presidential inaugurations. There are two full folders of slides taken by Mr. Lodge. The subjects vary, but all relate to some aspect of DC history such as the ceremony to light the National Christmas Tree and other events with political speakers. The dates of this series are 1949-1996 with the bulk of the material covering 1958-1966.
  - Presidential campaign bumper stickers, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Eisenhower, Reagan, and Ford
  - DC Republican Committee [newsletter], 12/1973-1976; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Slides of scenes of DC [1/2], 1958-1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    These slides incude topics such as Emancipation Day in front of the Lincoln Memorial, National Christmas Tree celebrations, Lyndon Johnson speaking, Udall Secretary of the Interior, Opening of DC Stadium (1961), 1960 Inaugural cake pavillion.
  - Slides of scenes of DC [2/2], 1958-1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    The topics of the slides in this folder include Republican event for Eisenhower, the first jet from Dulles airport (1962), Tomb of the Unknown Soldier and Arlington National Cemetery (November 11, 1958), fireworks on the Mall, Richard Nixon, Parade for General Charles De Gaulle (can see cars), aerial images taken from the Washington Monument (includes the Department of Agriculture building, Commerce Building, IRS, Justice Department etc.), Armed Forces Day, Winston Churchill in US (Summer 1959), White House protest ca. 1962 (not sure of the protest, but can see a sign that reads "Ban the Beatniks", Cherry Blossom festival 1962.
  - Dulles International Airport dedication program, 11/17/1962-11/18/1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Everett McKinley Dirksen Republican Forum, 03/20/1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General Douglas MacArthur funeral procession slides, 1964; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Inaugural souvenir Eisenhower/Nixon, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - John Glenn slides, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - John F. Kennedy inaugural materials, 1961; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - National Christmas Tree Celebration tickets, 1965-1971; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Rally, Young Republican Club of the District of Columbia [newsletter], 1958-1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Rally, Young Republican Club of the District of Columbia [newsletter], 1963-1966; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Republican party, 1972-1978; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Richard Nixon inaugural materials, 1972-1973; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ronald Reagan, 1981-1984; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Right [newsletter], 08/22/1966-09/29/1966; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Theater in Washington D.C., 1959-1977; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    These are playbills, tickets, and other materials related to theater in Washington D.C. It is likely Mr. Lodge attended these performances.
  - Tourism, 1962-1996; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    This folder contains the types of brochures and maps usually collected by tourists on a visit to Washington D.C. The topics include historic places such as the Washington Mounument, National Gallery, and Mount Vernon.
  - Washington National Eye Center, 1949-2003; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Young Republicans, 1958-1966; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    This material primarily relates to the District of Columbia Young Republicans and includes membership directories, and letters.
  - Young Republican election literature, 1962-1967; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1996; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    This folder contains correspondence from John Lodge to friends "Pat" and "Bill." The letters contain observations about Washington, D.C. politics and politians (including Senator McCarthy and President Ronald Reagan), as well as DC cultural events and buildings such as the National Gallery and the Hirschhorn.
- Teaching, 1958-2002; 1958-1978; Series 2; 0.25 Linear Feet 1/2 of a document box
  This series contains materials pertaining to John Lodge's teaching career at the George Washington University and the Washington Hospital Center. Materials include correspondence, speeches, schedules, programs, course descriptions, rosters, flyers, reports, brochures, and handbooks. Documents date between 1958 and 2002, with the majority of the material dating primarily between 1958 and 1978.
  Arranged alphabetically by institution and folder title.
  - Teaching--George Washington University, 1958-1977; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Teaching--George Washington University--2109 F Street, NW, 02/07/1978-09/26/1978; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Teaching--George Washington University--Correspondence, 05/03/1962-06/10/1996; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Teaching--Washington Hospital Center, 1966-2002; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Travel, 1953-1964; 1953-1956; Series 3; 1 Linear Feet 2 document boxes
  This series contains material related to John Lodge's travels to Japan, India, Kashmir, and Thailand between 1953 and 1956, as well as parts of the United States. Lodge served as Chief of Ophthalmology at the United States Air Force Misawa Air Base in Japan, and as a consulting ophthalmologist for the United States Army between 1953 and 1955. The materials cover Lodge's time at the Misawa Air base, as well as his site-seeing tours of Japan, India, Kashmir, and Thailand. Materials include pamphlets, brochures, maps, guides, souvenirs, programs, photographs, negatives, correspondence, postcards, U.S. Air Force-issued orders/assignments, and a ration book. Lodge also created extensive slides of his tours of Japan and India, many of which are accompanied by detailed typed descriptions.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title. Slides sets are primarily in the order in which Lodge kept them.
  - Travel--Flordia--Slides, 05/26/1964; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Travel--Flordia--Bok Tower, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Travel--India and Kashmir, circa 1955; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Travel--India--Delhi--"Babai Temple", 1954; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Travel--Japan and India--Tokyo and New Delhi--Slides, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Travel--Japan and India--Kyoto, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Travel--Japan, 1954-1956 and undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Travel--Japan, 04/19/1954; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Travel--Japan--Slides, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Travel--Japan--Slides, undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Travel--Japan--"Agou Falls", 04/15/1956; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Travel--Japan--"Art Museums, Chapel around Tokyo", 08/03/1955; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Travel--Japan--"The Best Scenes of Japanese Classical Drama (Kabuki)", 02/1954; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Travel--Japan--Buddhist Cultures, 03/23/1955; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Travel--Japan--"Glimpse of Japan Series, Kabuki Drama", 02/1954; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Travel--Japan--"Glimpse of Japan Series, Noh Play", undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Travel--Japan--Kyoto--"Buddha Temples", undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Travel--Japan--"Life in Japan", undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Travel--Japan--"Memory of Japan, Kyoto", undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Travel--Japan--"Nikko and Toyko Buddhist Temple", 11/10/1954; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Travel--Japan--Slides of Sightseeing, Osaka and Kobe", undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Travel--Japan--Tea Ceremony and Banquet--"Cha No Yu", undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Travel--Japan--Temples and Festivals, undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Travel--Japan--Tokyo, Nikko, Kamakura--Shrines of Japan, undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Travel--Japan--"Slides of Sightseeing, Tokyo", undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Travel--Japan--United States Air Force, Misawa Air Base, 1953-1955; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Travel--San Francisco, Hawaii, and Midway Island, 08/03/1955; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Travel--Thailand--"Temples of Bangkok, Siam", undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Travel--Pacific Ocean--Wake Island, undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Medical Reference Files, 1953-1982; 1953-1966; Series 4; 1.5 Linear Feet 1.5 document boxes
  This series contains the medical reference files of John Lodge. The files include hand-written notes, articles and clippings, pamphlets, essays, and lectures accumulated by Lodge on a variety of subjects related mainly to ophthamology. Materials date between 1953 and 1982, with the bulk of the material dating between 1953 and 1966.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title. The original order of these files has been maintained. The folder contents, therefore, may not always match the folder title.
  - Bacteriology, 1958-1981 and undated; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Cataracts, 1958-1964 and undated; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Cornea, 1953-1958 and undated; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - General, 1958-1966 and undated; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - General, 1958 and undated; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Glaucoma, 1957-1976 and undated; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Myopia, 1964-1982 and undated; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Neuro Ophthalmology, 1958 and undated; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Pathology, 1958-1977 and undated; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Physiological Optics, undated; Series 4 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Refraction, 1958-1962 and undated; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Notebooks, circa 1950-1951; Series 5; 1 Linear Feet 1.5 document boxes
  This series contains notebooks kept by John Lodge while a student at the Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, between 1947 and 1951.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Anatomy, circa 1947-1951; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Bacteriology, circa 1947-1951; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Laboratory, circa 1947-1951; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Medicine, circa 1947-1951; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1947-1951; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Pathology, circa 1947-1951; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Pediatrics, circa 1947-1951; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Pharmacology, circa 1947-1951; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Personal, 1946-2007; 1953-1970; Series 6; 0.25 Linear Feet 1/2 of a document box
  This series contains materials that document the major events in John Lodge's life. Included in this series is a biographical essay written by Lodge and versions of his curricula vitae, as well as photographs of Lodge alone, at his practice, with family members, and in class photographs from Bridgeport High School and Johns Hopkins University. The series also contains slides taken by Lodge of the campuses of Harvard University and the University of Wisconsin, and of class reunions for Bridgeport High School in West Virginia. The materials date between 1946 and 2007, with the bulk of the material dating between 1950 and 1970.
  - Personal, 1946-2007; 1953-1970; Series 6 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Personal--Class Reunion--Bridgeport High--Class of 1943--Slides, Series 6 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Personal--Class Reunion--Class of 1963--Slides, 07/1963; Series 6 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Personal--Class Reunion--Slides, 08/1993; Series 6 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Personal--Harvard and University of Wisconsin--Slides, undated; Series 6 (Box 7, Folder 8)